<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc3744 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.3744.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4791 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.4791.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4918 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.4918.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6352 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.6352.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6638 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.6638.xml'>
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName='dav-collection-sharing-00'>
    <front>
        <title abbrev="WebDAV Collection Sharing">WebDAV Collection Sharing</title>
        <author initials="C." surname="Daboo" fullname="Cyrus Daboo">
            <organization abbrev="Apple Inc.">
                Apple Inc.
            </organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>1 Infinite Loop</street>
                    <city>Cupertino</city>
                    <region>CA</region>
                    <code>95014</code>
                    <country>USA</country>
                </postal>
                <email>cyrus@daboo.name</email>
                <uri>http://www.apple.com/</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="E." surname="York" fullname="Eric York">
            <organization abbrev="Apple Inc.">
                Apple Inc.
            </organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>1 Infinite Loop</street>
                    <city>Cupertino</city>
                    <region>CA</region>
                    <code>95014</code>
                    <country>USA</country>
                </postal>
                <email></email>
                <uri>http://www.apple.com/</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author initials="E." surname="Pot" fullname="Evert Pot">
            <organization abbrev="fruux GmbH">
                fruux GmbH
            </organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Koenigsstrasse 32</street>
                    <city>Muenster</city>
                    <region>NRW</region>
                    <code>48143</code>
                    <country>Germany</country>
                </postal>
                <email>me@evertpot.com</email>
                <uri>https://fruux.com/</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date/>
        <abstract>
            <t>
                This specification defines an extension to WebDAV that enables the sharing of collections between users on a WebDAV server.
            </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <middle>

        <section title='Introduction'>

            <t>
                Users of <xref target="RFC4791">CalDAV</xref> and
                <xref target="RFC6352">CardDAV</xref> often require a
                mechanism to share a calendar or address book collection
                with other users.
            </t>
            <t>
                This specification introduces a mechanism that allows
                users of WebDAV servers to invite another user to a collection.
                The invited user can either accept or reject the invite, which
                is communicated back to the inviter.
                If the user chooses to accept the invite, the shared collection
                will then appear in a location on the server that's accessible
                by the invitee.
            </t>
            <t>
                There are existing mechanism that address similar use-cases,
                such as using <xref target='RFC3744'>WebDAV ACL</xref> for
                fine-grained access control. Experiences has shown that client
                developers are averse to using it due its complexity. Many
                implementations have chosen to only use WebDAV ACL for
                communicating access control information to clients, but not
                for modification. WebDAV ACL alone also does not provide the
                means for a user to invite another user.
            </t>
            <t>
                HTTP POST operations are used to manage the sharing invitations
                and replies, and WebDAV properties are used to expose the state
                of shared collections.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Open Issues">
            <t>
                <list style="numbers">
                    <t>Replying to invites can't happen on the calendar home, suggest to reply using the resource URI of the notification being replied to.</t>
                    <t>Doing this would allow dropping in-reply-to. An url is already an ID.</t>
                    <t>Consider removing DAV:href from in-reply-to as well. Should contain sharee, but seems unneeded.</t>
                    <t>Need mime-type for POST request xml bodies.</t>
                    <t>DAV:hosturl should probably be DAV:shared-url.</t>
                    <t>DAV:summary should probably be DAV:description</t>
                    <t>DAV:common-name should probably DAV:displayname</t>
                    <t>Move can-be-shared to an ACL privilege</t>
                    <t>Allow invite-deleted to also appear in DAV:user</t>
                    <t>Cleaning up notifications that have been replied to.</t>
                 </list>
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title='Conventions Used in This Document'>
            <t>
                The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target='RFC2119' />.
            </t>
            <t>
                When XML element types in the namespaces "DAV:" and "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:caldav" are referenced in this document outside of the context of an XML fragment, the string "DAV:" and "CALDAV:" will be prefixed to the element type names respectively.
            </t>
            <t>Terms Used:
                <list style='hanging'>
                    <t hangText='Sharer'>A user who is sharing a collection with other users.</t>
                    <t hangText='Sharee'>A user to whom a collection has been shared.</t>
                    <t hangText='Sharing Invite'>A message sent by a sharer to a sharee to indicate the status of a shared collection.</t>
                    <t hangText='Sharing Reply'>A message sent by a sharee to a sharer to indicate the status of a shared collection.</t>
                </list>
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title='Overview' anchor='overview'>
            <t>
                This section provides a basic overview of this protocol by way
                of a simple use case of a sharer sharing a collection with a
                single sharee.
            </t>
            <t>
                To share a collection with another user, the sharer's client
                executes an HTTP POST request against the collection resource
                for the collection to be shared. The POST request body will
                contain details of the user to whom the collection is to be
                shared as well as the access right to be granted to them. If
                the request succeeds, a notification is sent to the sharee
                with details of the collection being shared to them.
            </t>
            <t>
                The sharer's client will show the notification to the sharee
                and present them with the choice to accept or decline the
                invitation to the shared collection. If the sharee chooses to
                decline, then nothing changes for that sharee. If the sharee
                chooses to accept, then the server automatically creates a new
                collection resource in a location that is determined by the
                server.
                For example, if a <xref target='RFC4791'>CalDAV</xref> calendar
                is shared, the server may create the new collection in the
                sharee's calendar home.
                The server enforces the appropriate access privileges for the
                sharee.
            </t>
            <t>
                At any time, the sharer can inspect properties on the
                collection being shared, and determine the accept/decline
                status of each sharee. Additional sharees can be added and
                existing ones removed. The access privileges for existing
                sharees can also be changed.
            </t>
            <t>
                Once a sharee has access to the shared collection, they can
                remove it and decline the sharing invite by simply having
                their client issue an HTTP DELETE request on the shared
                collection. That does not delete any data, but rather simply
                removes the "link" to the sharer's collection and sets the
                sharee's invite status to declined.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Notification Definitions">
            <t>
                In order to facilitate the process of sharing invitations, this
                specification uses <!-- <xref target="dav-notifications">-->WebDAV
                notifications<!-- </xref> -->, and defines several new notification
                types.
            </t>
            <section title="Invite Notification" anchor='invite-notification'>
                <t>
                    When a sharer adds a new sharee to a collection, or updates
                    a sharee, an invite notification is added to the sharee's
                    notification collection.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The notification contains information about the shared
                    collection, the owner and how to respond to said invitation.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The body of this notification is retrieved with a GET
                    request. The root element of the notification MUST be
                    <xref target="DAV:invite-notification">DAV:invite-notification</xref>.
                </t>
                <section title="Example: An invite notification">
                    <t>
                        This is an example of a response to a GET request on a
                        correct invite notification. Note that several HTTP
                        response headers have been removed for brevity.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                    <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Content-Type: application/davnotification+xml
Content-Length: xxxx

<D:invite-notification xmlns:D="DAV:">
    <D:uid>I don't belong here</D:uid>
    <D:principal>
        <D:href>/principals/users/evert</D:href>
    </D:principal>
    <D:invite-accepted />
    <D:href>/calendars/users/evert/offdays/</D:href>
    <D:access><D:read-write /></D:access>
    <D:prop>
        <D:displayname>Vacation days!!</D:displayname>
    </D:prop>
</D:invite-notification>
]]></artwork>
                    </figure>
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section title="Invite Reply" anchor='invite-reply'>
                <t>
                    TODO
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title="Collection sharing">
            <section title="Feature Discovery">
                <t>
                    A server that supports the features described in this document MUST include "collection-sharing" as a field in the DAV response header from an OPTIONS request on any resource that supports these features.
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="Additional Properties for Collections" anchor='properties'>
                <t>
                    The following new or modified WebDAV properties are defined for collections and used to view or manipulate shared collection features.
                </t>
                <section title="DAV:resourcetype Property" anchor="DAV:resourcetype">
                    <t>
                        Collections that are shared have elements listed in their DAV:resourcetype property in addition to DAV:collection.
                        <list style="symbols">
                            <t><xref target="DAV:shared-owner">DAV:shared-owner</xref>: used to indicate that the colection is owned by the current user and is being shared by them.</t>
                            <t><xref target="DAV:shared">DAV:shared</xref>: used to indicate that the collection is owned by another user and is being shared to the current user.</t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="DAV:invite Property" anchor="DAV:invite">
                  <t>
                    <list style="hanging">
                      <t hangText="Name:">invite</t>
                      <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                      <t hangText="Purpose:">Used to show to whom a calendar has been shared.</t>
                      <t hangText="Protected:">This property MUST be protected.</t>
                      <t hangText="PROPFIND behavior:">This property SHOULD NOT be returned by a PROPFIND allprop request (as defined in Section 14.2 of <xref target="RFC4918"/>).</t>
                      <t hangText="COPY/MOVE behavior:">This property value MUST be preserved in MOVE operations, but MUST NOT be preserved in COPY operations.</t>

                      <t hangText="Description:">
                          This WebDAV property is present on a collection
                          resource that has been shared by the owner, or on
                          the collection resources for the sharees. It
                          provides a list of users to whom the collection has
                          been shared, along with the "status" of the sharing
                          invites sent to each user. In addition, servers
                          SHOULD include a DAV:organizer XML element on
                          collection resources of the sharees to provide
                          clients with a fast way to determine who the sharer
                          is. A server's local privacy policy may prevent
                          sharees from knowing about other sharees on a shared
                          calendar. If that is so server will not include
                          DAV:user XML elements for other sharees.
                      </t>
                      <t hangText="Definition:">
                        <figure>
                          <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT invite (organizer?, user*)>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                      </t>
                    </list>
                  </t>
                </section>
                <section title="DAV:allowed-sharing-modes Property" anchor="DAV:allowed-sharing-modes">
                  <t>
                    <list style="hanging">
                      <t hangText="Name:">allowed-sharing-modes</t>
                      <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                      <t hangText="Purpose:">Used to show which modes of sharing are supported on a calendar collection.</t>
                      <t hangText="Protected:">This property MUST be protected.</t>
                      <t hangText="PROPFIND behavior:">This property SHOULD NOT be returned by a PROPFIND allprop request (as defined in Section 14.2 of <xref target="RFC4918"/>).</t>
                      <t hangText="COPY/MOVE behavior:">This property value MUST be preserved in COPY and MOVE operations.</t>

                      <t hangText="Description:">
                          This WebDAV property is present on a collection
                          resource that can be shared. It provides a list of
                          options indicating what sharing modes are allowed as
                          per <xref target="allowed"/>.
                      </t>
                      <t hangText="Definition:">
                        <figure>
                          <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT allowed-sharing-modes
          (can-be-shared?)>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                      </t>
                    </list>
                  </t>
                </section>
                <section title="DAV:shared-url Property" anchor="DAV:shared-url">
                  <t>
                    <list style="hanging">
                      <t hangText="Name:">shared-url</t>
                      <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                      <t hangText="Purpose:">Indicates the URL of the owner's copy of a shared collection.</t>
                      <t hangText="Protected:">This property MUST be protected.</t>
                      <t hangText="PROPFIND behavior:">This property SHOULD NOT be returned by a PROPFIND allprop request (as defined in Section 14.2 of <xref target="RFC4918"/>).</t>
                      <t hangText="COPY/MOVE behavior:">This property value MUST be preserved in COPY and MOVE operations.</t>

                      <t hangText="Description:">
                          This WebDAV property is present on a shared
                          collection resource that appears in a sharee's
                          calendar home collection. Its content is a single
                          DAV:href element whose value is the URL of the
                          sharer's calendar being shared.
                      </t>
                      <t hangText="Definition:">
                        <figure>
                          <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT shared-url (DAV:href)>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                      </t>
                    </list>
                  </t>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section title="Sharer Actions on Shared Collections">
                <section title="Sharing or Unsharing a Collection">
                    <t>
                        To update an existing collection to be shared, the
                        sharer simply adds one or more sharees to the
                        collection as per <xref target="sharee"/>. The server
                        MUST update the DAV:resourcetype property on the
                        calendar collection to ensure it contains a
                        DAV:shared-owner XML element to indicate the calendar
                        collection is now shared.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        To unshare a collection, the sharer simply removes all
                        sharees to the CS:invite property of the collection as
                        per <xref target="sharee"/>. The server MUST update the
                        DAV:resourcetype property on the calendar collection
                        to ensure it does not contain a CS:shared-owner XML
                        element to indicate the collection is not shared.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="Manipulating Sharees of a Shared Collection" anchor="sharee">
                    <t>
                        The sharer of a shared collection is able to manipulate
                        the sharee list by issuing a POST request targeted at
                        the calendar collection resource. The POST request MUST
                        contain an XML document as its body with the root
                        element being <xref target="DAV:share">DAV:share</xref>.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The <xref target="DAV:share">DAV:share</xref> element in
                        the POST requests MUST contain one or more
                        <xref target="DAV:set">DAV:set</xref> or
                        <xref target="DAV:remove">DAV:remove</xref> elements.
                        For each <xref target="DAV:set">CS:set</xref> element,
                        the server MUST add the specified sharee access to the
                        collection. For each
                        <xref target="DAV:remove">DAV:remove</xref> element
                        the server MUST remove the specified sharee access
                        from the shared collection. In each case the server MUST
                        send a notification message to any sharees whose status
                        is changed (added, modified or removed), indicating to
                        them a change in status for the shared collection. The
                        server SHOULD NOT send notification messages to sharees
                        whose status is unchanged.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Sharees are identified via a DAV:href element whose
                        value is either a principal-URL for a sharee hosted on
                        the same server, an email address, or any other URI
                        identifying a user.
                        In the case of the later two, the sharee might not be
                        a user on the same server - though in that case how
                        invitations are sent or access enabled is out of scope
                        for this specification. A server MAY change the
                        sharee's "address" to any suitable alternative that
                        it might prefer when returning the list of sharees via
                        the <xref target="DAV:invite">DAV:invite property</xref>.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The client MAY include a
                        <xref target="DAV:common-name">DAV:common-name</xref>
                        element in the <xref target="DAV:set">DAV:set</xref>
                        element. When provided, the value represents the common
                        name for the sharee, and is returned in the list of
                        sharees via the <xref target="DAV:invite">DAV:invite property</xref>.
                        The server MAY change this to a suitable alternative
                        when it is able to match the sharee to a known user.
                        If absent from the client request, the server SHOULD
                        add a CS:common-name when it is able to match the
                        sharee with a known user, and a common name for that
                        user can be determined.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        When the sharee list on a shared collection is changed,
                        the server MUST send notifications to each sharee to
                        update them on their current sharing status. This is
                        accomplished by sending a
                        <xref target="DAV:invite-notification">DAV:invite-notification</xref>
                        notification to each sharee.
                    </t>
                    <section title="Example: Successful Sharee Add Request">

                        <t>
                          This example shows how to add a single sharee (with email address "mailto:eric@example.com") to a shared collection with DAV:read-write access.
                        </t>

                        <figure>
                          <preamble>&gt;&gt; Request &lt;&lt;</preamble>
                          <artwork><![CDATA[
POST /calendars/users/cyrus/shared/ HTTP/1.1
Host: calendar.example.com
Content-Type: application/xml; charset="utf-8"
Content-Length: xxxx

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<D:share xmlns:D="DAV:">
  <D:set>
    <D:href>mailto:eric@example.com</D:href>
    <D:common-name>Eric York</D:common-name>
    <D:summary>Shared workspace</D:summary>
    <D:read-write />
  </D:set>
</D:share>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                        <figure>
                          <preamble>&gt;&gt; Response &lt;&lt;</preamble>
                          <artwork><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Cache-Control: no-cache
Date: Sat, 11 Nov 2006 09:32:12 GMT]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </section>
                    <section title="Example: Successful Multiple Sharee Change Request">

                        <t>
                            This example shows how multiple sharee's can be manipulated in a single request. The sharee with email address "mailto:eric@example.com" has their access downgraded to CS:read, whilst another sharee is removed from the access list entirely.
                        </t>

                        <figure>
                          <preamble>&gt;&gt; Request &lt;&lt;</preamble>
                          <artwork><![CDATA[
POST /calendars/users/cyrus/shared/ HTTP/1.1
Host: calendar.example.com
Content-Type: application/xml; charset="utf-8"
Content-Length: xxxx

<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<D:share xmlns:D="DAV:">
  <D:set>
    <D:href>mailto:eric@example.com</D:href>
    <D:summary>Shared workspace</D:summary>
    <D:read-write />
  </D:set>
  <D:remove>
    <D:href>mailto:wilfredo@example.com</D:href>
  </D:remove>
</D:share>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                        <figure>
                          <preamble>&gt;&gt; Response &lt;&lt;</preamble>
                          <artwork><![CDATA[
HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Cache-Control: no-cache
Date: Sat, 11 Nov 2006 09:32:12 GMT]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                    </section>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section title="Sharee Actions on Shared Collections">
                <section title="Replying to a Sharing Invite">
                    <t>
                        When a sharee is invited to a shared collection they
                        can accept or decline the invite by issuing a POST
                        request to the sharee's notification collection
                        resource. The POST request MUST contain an XML
                        document as its body with the root element being
                        <xref target="DAV:invite-reply">DAV:invite-reply</xref>.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The <xref target="DAV:invite-reply">DAV:invite-reply</xref>
                        element in the POST request specifies the sharee who is
                        replying in the DAV:href element, the accept or decline
                        action via the DAV:invite-accepted or
                        DAV:invite-declined elements, the URL of the shared
                        collection in the DAV:hosturl element, the unique
                        identifier of the invite to which it is a reply in the
                        DAV:in-reply-to element, and an optional DAV:summary
                        element.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        The response to a POST request that accepts a shared
                        collection invite MUST be an XML document containing
                        <xref target="DAV:shared-as">DAV:shared-as</xref> as its
                        root element. That root element contains a single
                        DAV:href element whose content is the URI of the shared
                        collection somewhere on the server that the sharee has
                        access to.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        When the sharee replies to an invite, the server
                        SHOULD send a notification to the sharer to update
                        them on the change in the sharee state. This is
                        accomplished by sending a
                        <xref target="DAV:invite-reply">DAV:invite-reply</xref>
                        notification to the sharer.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        After the sharee has issued a reply, the server SHOULD
                        also remove the notification that contained the
                        initial invite.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="Removing a Shared Collection">
                    <t>
                        To remove a shared collection a DELETE request is
                        targeted at the shared collection URI. When such a
                        request is received the server MUST remove the shared
                        collection and automatically update the sharee's
                        status in the sharer's DAV:invite property.
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section title="General Considerations">
                <section title="Access Levels">
                    <t>
                        Two levels of access ca be granted by a sharer to any sharee. These are governed by the DAV:access element used in the DAV:invite/DAV:user element that specifies a shared user invite. DAV:access contains a single empty element that defines the type of access granted:
                        <list style="hanging">
                        <t hangText="DAV:read">
                            When present this indicates that sharees can read information from the collection, but cannot change it.
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="DAV:read-write">
                            When present this indicates that sharees can read and write collection data.
                        </t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="Allowing or Disallowing Sharing" anchor="allowed">
                    <t>
                        Servers MAY support sharing on a per-collections basis
                        - e.g., they could treat some collections as always
                        private (cannot be shared) or always public (always
                        shared). As a result clients need a way to determine
                        which collection could be shared so they can enable or
                        disable sharing options on a per-collection basis.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        This specification adds a <xref target="DAV:allowed-sharing-modes">DAV:allowed-sharing-modes</xref> WebDAV property which servers can return on collection resources. This property contains XML elements that describe which sharing capabilities can be supported by the corresponding collection:
                        <list>
                            <t><xref target="DAV:can-be-shared">DAV:can-be-shared</xref>: when present indicates that the collection can be shared. When not present, the collection cannot be shared.</t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        When not present on a collection, sharing that collection is not allowed. Clients SHOULD NOT attempt to use requests to enable sharing targeted at those collections.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="Per-instance WebDAV Properties" anchor="per-instance-data">
                    <t>
                        Servers MUST support "per-instance" WebDAV properties
                        on shared collections and MAY support them on resources
                        within shared collections. A "per-instance" WebDAV
                        property is one whose value can be set and retrieved
                        on an instance of a collection, but is not
                        automatically propagated to other instances of the
                        same shared collection. For example, a sharee may
                        change a property on their instance of a shared
                        collection, but the instance of the owner of the
                        collection will not see this updated value.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        For shared collections, the server MUST allow all
                        users to write "per-instance" WebDAV properties on the
                        shared collection and MAY allow property writes on
                        resources within the shared collection. This is
                        required even in the case where the sharee has been
                        granted read access only (i.e., the ability to
                        change the calenar is disallowed). This requirement
                        ensures that sharees can always change "personal"
                        properties such as display names.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Servers MUST treat the following properties as "per-instance":
                        <list>
                            <t>DAV:displayname</t>
                        </list>
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Servers MAY treat any dead property as per-instance.
                    </t>
                    <t>
                        Servers MUST NOT treat live properties as per-instance.
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title='XML Element Definitions'>
            <section title="DAV:shared-owner" anchor="DAV:shared-owner">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">shared-owner</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Used to indicate that a collection is being shared by the owner.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">This property appears in the DAV:resourcetype property on the collection resource shared by a sharer. See <xref target="properties"/>.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT shared-owner EMPTY>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:shared" anchor="DAV:shared">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">shared</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Used to indicate that a collection is being shared to a sharee.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">This property appears in the DAV:resourcetype property on a collection resource that is shared to a sharee. See <xref target="properties"/>.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT shared EMPTY>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:can-be-shared" anchor="DAV:can-be-shared">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">can-be-shared</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Used to indicate that a collection can be shared.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">This element indicates that a collection can be shared with other users. See <xref target="DAV:allowed-sharing-modes"/></t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT can-be-shared EMPTY>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:user" anchor="DAV:user">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">user</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Used to show status of sharing invites sent to sharees.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">This element provides the "status" of a sharing invite sent to a particular user. See <xref target="DAV:invite"/>.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT user (DAV:href, common-name?, (invite-noresponse |
                invite-accepted | invite-declined | invite-invalid),
                access, summary?)>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:invite-noresponse">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">invite-noresponse</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Sharing invite status.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">When used in a <xref target="DAV:user">DAV:user</xref> element, this element is used to indicate that the sharee has never replied to the corresponding sharing invite. When used in a <xref target="DAV:invite-notification">DAV:invite-notification</xref> element, this element is used to indicate to the sharee that a sharing reply is needed.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT invite-noresponse EMPTY>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:invite-deleted">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">invite-deleted</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Sharing invite status.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">When used in a <xref target="DAV:invite-notification">DAV:invite-notification</xref> element, this element is used to indicate to the sharee that a shared collection has been unshared by the sharer.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT invite-deleted EMPTY>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:invite-accepted">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">invite-accepted</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Sharing invite status.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">When used in a <xref target="DAV:user">DAV:user</xref> element, this element is used to indicate that the sharee has accepted the corresponding sharing invite. When used in a <xref target="DAV:invite-notification">DAV:invite-notification</xref> element, this element is used to indicate to the sharee that the sharing invite is an update for one they previously accepted.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT invite-accepted EMPTY>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:invite-declined">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">invite-declined</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Sharing invite status.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">When used in a <xref target="DAV:user">DAV:user</xref> element, this element is used to indicate that the sharee has declined the corresponding sharing invite. When used in a <xref target="DAV:invite-notification">DAV:invite-notification</xref> element, this element is used to indicate to the sharee that the sharing invite is an update for one they previously declined.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT invite-declined EMPTY>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:invite-invalid">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">invite-invalid</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Sharing invite status.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">When used in a <xref target="DAV:user">DAV:user</xref> element, this element is used to indicate that the corresponding sharee is not a valid user known to the server.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT invite-invalid EMPTY>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:access">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">access</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Shared collection access level.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">When used in a <xref target="DAV:user">DAV:user</xref> element, this element is used to indicate the sharing access level granted to the corresponding sharee.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT access (read | read-write)>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:read">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">read</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Shared collection access level privilege.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">Indicates that the access level granted only allows sharees to read data in the shared collection (though they can write <xref target="per-instance-data">per-instance data</xref>).</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT read EMPTY>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:read-write">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">read-write</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Shared collection access level privilege.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">Indicates that the access level granted allows sharees to read and write all data in the collection.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT read-write EMPTY>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:summary">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">summary</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Summary or title of shared collection.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">A brief description of a shared collection. This can be used by sharers to communicate the nature of a shared collection to sharees, as well as used by sharees to indicate back to the sharer how each sharee is refering to the shared collection.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT summary (#PCDATA)>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:invite-notification" anchor="DAV:invite-notification">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">invite-notification</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">A notification used as a shared collection invite.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">Defines a notification message sent automatically by the server when a sharer adds, changes or removes a sharee from a shared collection. The DAV:href element specifies the URI of the sharee to whom the message was sent.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT invite-notification (
            uid, dav:href,
            (invite-noresponse | invite-deleted |
            invite-accepted | invite-declined),
            access, hosturl, organizer,
            summary?,
>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:uid">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">uid</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Unique identifier.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">A unique identifier for an invitation to a collection.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT uid (#PCDATA)>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:hosturl">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">hosturl</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Identifies the source URL of a shared collection.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">Contains a single DAV:href element that refers to the source of a shared collection - i.e., the URL of the collection shared by the sharer.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT hosturl (DAV:href)>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:organizer">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">organizer</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Identifies the sharer of a shared collection.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">Contains a single DAV:href element that identifies the URI of the sharer of a shared collection, and an optional DAV:common-name element that matches that user, and an optional DAV:first-name, DAV:last-name pair of elements that match that user. In some cases servers might have directory information that includes only the common name, or only the first or last name, and it is better to expose those directly to the client as-is rather than to try and split or combine the attributes to synthesize one set or the other.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT organizer (DAV:href,
                     DAV:common-name?,
                     (DAV:first-name, DAV:last-name)?)>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:common-name" anchor="DAV:common-name">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">common-name</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">The common name of a sharer or sharee.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">The common name is optionally provided by a client when adding a sharee and optionally included (or modified) by the server when returning results for sharers or sharees and in notifications.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT common-name (#PCDATA)>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:first-name" anchor="DAV:first-name">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">first-name</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">The first name of a sharer or sharee.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">The first name is optionally included by the server when returning results for sharers or sharees and in notifications.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT first-name (#PCDATA)>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:last-name" anchor="DAV:last-name">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">last-name</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">The last name of a sharer or sharee.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">The last name is optionally included by the server when returning results for sharers or sharees and in notifications.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT last-name (#PCDATA)>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:invite-reply" anchor="DAV:invite-reply">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">invite-reply</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">A notification used as a reply to a shared collection invite.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">Defines a notification message sent automatically by the server when a sharee replies to a shared collection invite. The DAV:href element specifies the URI of the sharee to whom the original invite message was sent.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT invite-reply (DAV:href,
                        (invite-accepted | invite-declined),
                        hosturl, in-reply-to, summary?>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:in-reply-to">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">in-reply-to</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Unique identifier.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">Specifies the unique identifier of the inviate message that this notification message is a reply to.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT in-reply-to (#PCDATA)>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:share" anchor="DAV:share">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">share</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Describes changes to sharees.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">The root element used in POST requests on collections by sharers to manipulate the sharee list of a shared collections.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT share (set | remove)*>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:set" anchor="DAV:set">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">set</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Sets access for a sharee.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">Used to add or modify sharee access to a shared collection. The specified access to the shared collection is given to the sharee.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT set (DAV:href, common-name?, summary?,
               (read | read-write)>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:remove" anchor="DAV:remove">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">remove</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Removes access for a sharee.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">Used to remove sharee access to a shared collection. All access to the shared collection is removed for the sharee.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT remove (DAV:href)>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
            <section title="DAV:shared-as" anchor="DAV:shared-as">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">shared-as</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Identifies a shared collection.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">Returned by the server for a POST request by a sharee accepting a shared collection invite. The DAV:href element specifies the URI of the collection created by the acceptance.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT shared-as (DAV:href)>]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title='Security Considerations'>
            <t>
                TBD
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title='IANA Considerations'>
            <t>
                This document does not require any actions on the part of IANA.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title='Acknowledgments'>
            <t>
                This specification is the result of discussions between the Apple calendar server and client teams.
            </t>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title='Normative References'>
            &rfc2119;
            &rfc3744;
            &rfc4791;
            &rfc4918;
            &rfc6352;
            &rfc6638;
        </references>
<!--
<references title='Informative References'>
</references>
-->
        <section title='Change History'>
            <t>Changes in -03:
                <list style='numbers'>
                    <t>Fixed access element DTD.</t>
                    <t>Remove MKxxx and PROPPATCH mechanism for upgrading/downgrading shared state on a calendar collection. Instead the server implicitly sets the state based on whether there are any sharees or not..</t>
                    <t>Added CS:first-name and CS:last-name optional element to CS:organizer.</t>
                    <t>Added CALDAV:supported-calendar-component-set optional element to CS:invite-notification.</t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t>Changes in -02:
                <list style='numbers'>
                    <t>Removed read-write-shared access mode - now a server that does not support shared scheduling should advertise that via a DAV header</t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t>Changes in -01:
                <list style='numbers'>
                    <t>Added CS:shared-url property</t>
                    <t>Clarified that notifications are only required to be sent when sharee status is changed</t>
                </list>
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title='Backwards compatibility'>
            <t>
                This specification is based on an earlier effort, often referred
                to as 'caldav-sharing'. It is possible to remain compatibile with
                this specification, but it's important to be aware of a number of
                changes.
            </t>
            <t>
                The earlier draft uses the http://calendarserver.org/ns/
                namespace for all its xml elements. This means that any
                WebDAV property introduced in this specification, may need
                to have a similar property in the old namespace.
            </t>
            <t>
                XML documentations as sent by POST requests and responses, and
                resources returned from notifications can be distinguished by
                the use of the Content-Type and Accept HTTP headers. The earlier
                draft does not define new mime-types for these, but this
                specification does.
            </t>
        </section>
    </back>
</rfc>
