<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc3339 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.3339.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc3744 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.3744.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4791 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.4791.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc4918 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.4918.xml'>
<!ENTITY rfc6352 PUBLIC '' 'bibxml/reference.RFC.6352.xml'>
]>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc private="Calendar Server Extension"?>
<rfc ipr="none" docName='webdav-notifications-00'>
    <front>
        <title abbrev="WebDAV User Notifications">WebDAV: User Notifications</title>
        <author initials="C." surname="Daboo" fullname="Cyrus Daboo">
            <organization abbrev="Apple Inc.">
                Apple Inc.
            </organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>1 Infinite Loop</street>
                    <city>Cupertino</city>
                    <region>CA</region>
                    <code>95014</code>
                    <country>USA</country>
                </postal>
                <email>cyrus@daboo.name</email>
                <uri>http://www.apple.com/</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date/>
        <abstract>
            <t>
                This specification defines an extension to WebDAV that allows the server to provide notifications to users.
            </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section title='Introduction'>
            <t>
                It is often useful for servers to communicate arbitrary
                information to the end-users for a WebDAV system, such as a
                system status, message of the day or changes to changes made
                to shared resources by other users.
           </t>
           <t>
               This specification defines a generic "notification" mechanism
               that allows a server to do that. Whilst primarily aimed at
               <xref target="RFC4791">CalDAV</xref> and <xref target="RFC6352">CardDAV</xref>
               this mechanism has been designed to be adaptable to other
               applications of <xref target='RFC4918'>WebDAV</xref>.
           </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Open Issues">
            <t>
                <list style="numbers">
                    <t>Define specific child elements for system status notification, e.g. "server-maintenance-period", "server-read-only-period", "client-upgrade-required".</t>
                </list>
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title='Conventions Used in This Document'>
            <t>
                The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target='RFC2119' />.
            </t>
            <t>
                When XML element types in the namespaces "DAV:" is referenced
                in this document outside of the context of an XML fragment,
                the string "DAV:" will be prefixed to the element type name.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Requirements Overview">
            <t>
                To add support for WebDAV notifications, a server MUST at
                least have support for <xref target="RFC4918">WebDAV Class 3</xref>.
            </t>
            <t>
                WebDAV notifications also defines new properties on principal
                resources, which are defined in <xref target="RFC3744">RFC3744</xref>.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section title="Notifications">
            <t>When this feature is available, a <xref target="DAV:notification-URL">DAV:notification-URL</xref> property appears on principal resources for those principals who are able to receive notifications. That property specifies a single DAV:href element whose content refers to a WebDAV collection resource. Notification "messages" are deposited into this collection and can be retrieved by clients and acted on accordingly.</t>
            <t>The notification collection referenced by the <xref target="DAV:notification-URL">DAV:notification-URL</xref> property MUST have a DAV:resourcetype property with DAV:collection and <xref target="DAV:notifications">DAV:notifications</xref> child elements.</t>
            <t>Notification "messages" are XML documents stored as resources in the notification collection. Each XML document contains a <xref target="DAV:notification">DAV:notification</xref> element as its root. The root element contains a DAV:dtstamp element, and one additional element which represents the type of notification being conveyed in the message. That child element will typically contain additional content that describes the notification.</t>
            <t>Each notification resource has a <xref target="DAV:notificationtype">DAV:notificationtype</xref> property which contains as its single child element an empty element that matches the child element of the notification resource XML document root. Any attributes on the child element in the XML document are also present in the property child element.</t>
            <t>Notifications are automatically generated by the server with an appropriate resource stored in the notifications collection of the user to whom the notification is targeted. Clients SHOULD monitor the notification collection looking for new notification resources. When doing so, clients SHOULD look at the <xref target="DAV:notificationtype">DAV:notificationtype</xref> property to ensure that the notification is of a type that the client can handle. Once a client has handled the notification in whatever way is appropriate it SHOULD delete the notification resource. Clients SHOULD remove notifications being displayed to a user when the notification resource is removed from the notification collection, to enable the user to dismiss a notification on one device and have it automatically removed from others. Clients MUST ignore all notifications for types they do not recognize. Servers MAY delete notification resources on their own if they determine that the notifications are no longer relevant or valid. Servers MAY coalesce notifications as appropriate.</t>
            <t>Servers MUST prevent clients from adding resources in the notification collection.</t>
            <section title="Additional Principal Properties" anchor='principal-properties'>
                <t>This section defines new properties for WebDAV principal resources as defined in <xref target="RFC3744">RFC3744</xref>. These properties are likely to be protected but the server MAY allow them to be written by appropriate users.</t>
                <section title="DAV:notification-URL Property" anchor="DAV:notification-URL">
                  <t>
                    <list style="hanging">
                      <t hangText="Name:">notification-URL</t>
                      <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                      <t hangText="Purpose:">Identify the URL of the notification collection owned by the associated principal resource.</t>
                      <t hangText="Protected:">This property SHOULD be protected.</t>
                      <t hangText="PROPFIND behavior:">This property SHOULD NOT be returned by a PROPFIND allprop request (as defined in Section 14.2 of <xref target="RFC4918"/>).</t>
                      <t hangText="COPY/MOVE behavior:">This property value SHOULD be preserved in COPY and MOVE operations.</t>

                      <t hangText="Description:">This property is needed for a client to determine where the notification collection of the current user is located so that processing of notification messages can occur. If not present, then the associated calendar user is not enabled for notification messages on the server.</t>
                      <t hangText="Definition:">
                        <figure>
                          <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT notification-URL (DAV:href)>]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                      </t>
                    </list>
                  </t>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section title="Properties on Notification Resources" anchor='notification-properties'>
                <t>The following new WebDAV properties are defined for notification resources.</t>
                <section title="DAV:notificationtype Property" anchor="DAV:notificationtype">
                  <t>
                    <list style="hanging">
                      <t hangText="Name:">notificationtype</t>
                      <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                      <t hangText="Purpose:">Identify the type of notification of the corresponding resource.</t>
                      <t hangText="Protected:">This property MUST be protected.</t>
                      <t hangText="PROPFIND behavior:">This property SHOULD NOT be returned by a PROPFIND allprop request (as defined in Section 14.2 of <xref target="RFC4918"/>).</t>
                      <t hangText="COPY/MOVE behavior:">This property value MUST be preserved in COPY and MOVE operations.</t>

                      <t hangText="Description:">This property allows a client, via a PROPFIND Depth:1 request, to quickly find notification messages that the client can handle in a notification collection. The single child element is the notification resource root element's child defining the notification itself. This element MUST be empty, though any attributes on the element in the notification resource MUST be present in the property element.</t>
                      <t hangText="Definition:">
                        <figure>
                          <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT notificationtype ANY>
<!-- Child elements are empty but will have appropriate attributes.
     Any valid notification message child element can appear.-->]]></artwork>
                        </figure>
                      </t>
                    </list>
                  </t>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section title='XML Element Definitions'>
                <section title="DAV:notifications" anchor="DAV:notifications">
                    <t>
                      <list style="hanging">
                        <t hangText="Name:">notifications</t>
                        <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                        <t hangText="Purpose:">Indicates a notification collection.</t>
                        <t hangText="Description:">This XML element is used in a DAV:resourcetype element to indicate that the corresponding resource is a notification collection.</t>
                        <t hangText="Definition:">
                          <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT notifications EMPTY>]]></artwork>
                          </figure>
                        </t>
                      </list>
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section title="DAV:notification" anchor="DAV:notification">
                    <t>
                      <list style="hanging">
                        <t hangText="Name:">notification</t>
                        <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                        <t hangText="Purpose:">Notification message root element.</t>
                        <t hangText="Description:">The root element used in notification resources.</t>
                        <t hangText="Definition:">
                          <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT notification (dtstamp, XXX) >
<!-- Any notification type element can appear after
     DAV:dtstamp -->]]></artwork>
                          </figure>
                        </t>
                      </list>
                    </t>
                </section>
              <section title="DAV:dtstamp" anchor="DAV:dtstamp">
                <t>
                  <list style="hanging">
                    <t hangText="Name:">dtstamp</t>
                    <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                    <t hangText="Purpose:">Date-time stamp.</t>
                    <t hangText="Description:">Contains the date-time stamp corresponding to the creation of a notification message, using the format defined in <xref target="RFC3339"/>, or the "compact" format without "-" and ":" characters between date and time elements, respectively.</t>
                    <t hangText="Definition:">
                      <figure>
                        <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT dtstamp (#PCDATA)>
<!-- Value is a date-time in UTZ as per [RFC3339] with
     "compact" format allowed.-->]]></artwork>
                      </figure>
                    </t>
                  </list>
                </t>
              </section>
            </section>

        </section>

        <section title="Notification Definitions">
            <t>This section defines a set of common notification types.</t>
            <section title="System Status Notification">
                <t>The system status notification is used to convey a URI and/or textual description to the user. The assumption is that the URI points to a webpage where current system status is described in detail, with the provided description being a summary of that. A "type" attribute on the element is used to indicate the importance of the current status notification, and has the values "low", "medium" and "high", representing the increasing level of importance of the message respectively.</t>
                <t>Servers might have knowledge of specific calendar user language preferences, in which case it MAY localise the DAV:description value as appropriate based on the calendar user accessing the notification, but if it does, it SHOULD include an xml:lang attribute on the DAV:description element to indicate what language is being used.</t>
                <section title="DAV:systemstatus Element Definition" anchor="DAV:systemstatus">
                    <t>
                      <list style="hanging">
                        <t hangText="Name:">systemstatus</t>
                        <t hangText="Namespace:">DAV:</t>
                        <t hangText="Purpose:">Indicates a system status notification.</t>
                        <t hangText="Description:">This XML element is used in a DAV:notification element to describe a system status notification.</t>
                        <t hangText="Definition:">
                          <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[
<!ELEMENT systemstatus (DAV:href?, DAV:description?)>
<!ATTLIST systemstatus type (low | medium | high) "low">

  <!ELEMENT description CDATA>

<!-- One of DAV:href of DAV:description MUST be present -->
]]></artwork>
                          </figure>
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Example:">This is an example of the body of a notification resource for an emergency system outage:
                          <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<D:notification xmlns:D="DAV:">
  <D:dtstamp>2011-12-09T11:12:53-05:00</D:dtstamp>
  <D:systemstatus type="high">
    <D:href>http://example.com/emergency_shutdown.html</D:href>
    <D:description xml:lang='en_US'
    >Emergency shutdown now</D:description>
  </D:systemstatus>
</D:notification>]]></artwork>
                          </figure>
                        </t>
                        <t hangText="Example:">This is an example of the WebDAV property on the example notification resource above:
                          <figure>
                            <artwork><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<D:notificationtype xmlns:D="DAV:">
  <D:systemstatus type="high" />
</D:notificationtype>]]></artwork>
                          </figure>
                        </t>
                      </list>
                    </t>
                </section>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section title='Security Considerations'>
            <t>Some notification mechanisms might allow a user to trigger a notification to be delivered to other users (e.g., an invitation to share a calendar). In such cases servers MUST ensure that suitable limits are placed on the number and frequency of such user generated notifications.</t>
            <t>
                TBD: More?
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title='IANA Considerations'>
            <t>
                This document does not require any actions on the part of IANA.
            </t>
        </section>
        <section title='Acknowledgments'>
            <t>
                This specification is the result of discussions between the various Apple calendar server and client teams.
            </t>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
        <references title='Normative References'>
            &rfc2119;
            &rfc3339;
            &rfc4918;
        </references>
        <references title='Informative References'>
            &rfc3744;
            &rfc4791;
        </references>
        <!--
        <section title='Change History'>
            <t>Changes in -01:
                <list style='numbers'>
                    <t></t>
                </list>
            </t>
        </section>
        -->
    </back>
</rfc>
